Finding Aid for Richard H. Headlee papers 1976-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard H. Headlee papers 1976-1992
Headlee, Richard H., 1930-2004
1 oversize folders
7 linear feet
Life insurance executive, leader of a citizens tax limitation movement in Michigan, officer of Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation. Subject files relating to the tax limitation movement in Michigan, especially the work of Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation and Taxpayers United Federation; includes photographs, video cassettes, and news clippings.
89157 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Richard H. Headlee (Donor No. 7604 ) in 1988 and 1994.
The collection is open for research.
Richard H. Headlee was born in Fort Dodge, Iowa in 1930. He gained political experience as an advisor to Michigan Governor George Romney from 1966 until 1968, before returning to private business. He was first named president of a small industrial firm and, in 1972, was selected to be president of the Alexander Hamilton Life Insurance Company in Farmington Hills, Michigan. After the failure of the 1976 tax amendment campaign, Headlee was asked to assume the chairmanship of Taxpayers United.
Headlee conducted a vigorous and successful campaign across Michigan and won approval for Proposal E in November 1978. Also called the "Headlee Amendment," Proposal E limited the increase of taxes to the growth of personal income of Michigan residents.
In 1979 the Taxpayers United organization merged with the Taxpayers Federation of Michigan. The new organization was named Taxpayers United Federation, Inc., and its primary purpose was to lobby state legislators in Lansing for a favorable interpretation and implementation of the "Headlee Amendment."
Headlee's political activities continued through the 1980s. He mounted an unsuccessful campaign for governor in 1988 on the Republican ticket. His organization, Taxpayers United, was more successful, running a number of statewide campaigns to further reduce taxes and government spending and shift power to local governments from the state. Most notable of these was the "Headlee Initiative," a statewide ballot initiative to limit state spending increases to the rate of inflation. The governor and state government and legislature opposed this initiative and, in a controversial decision, the State Board of Canvassers found that enough signatures were invalid to deny the petition's passage. Taxpayers United took the Board of Canvassers to court, and ultimately won, placing the initiative on the ballot in 1992. The initiative became state law after the elections that November.
The Richard H. Headlee Papers document the activities of the principal leader of the "tax revolt" in Michigan in the 1970s and 1980s. The papers include material on the major organizations Headlee founded or was affiliated with, the voter initiative which resulted in passage of Proposal E (the "Headlee Amendment") restricting growth in property taxes, and Headlee's campaign for governor in 1988.
The papers were received in two major accessions. The first, received in 1988, has been arranged in three series: Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation, Taxpayers United Federation, and Topical Files. The second accession, received in 1994, has been divided into six series: Correspondence, Headlee for Governor (1988), Headlee Initiative, Taxpayers United for the Michigan Constitution, Visual Materials, and Clippings.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1978.; Headlee, Richard H. (Richard Harold), 1930-2004; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.; Taxation--Michigan.; Taxpayers United Federation.; Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Headlee, Richard H. (Richard Harold), 1930-2004; North, Oliver.; Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.; Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation 1976-1979
  Of particular interest in the Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation series are the William Shaker materials, the Richard H. Headlee speeches, and the slide show scripts and audio tape. William Shaker founded the Taxpayers United organization in 1974 and served as a board member thereafter. Headlee's speeches and slide show presentations throughout Michigan in 1977 and 1978 contributed much to the popular success of the 1978 tax amendment campaign. This series also contains a set of media and publicity materials including three folders of newspaper clippings, one folder of television-radio news and editorial scripts, and two folders of press releases relating to the 1978 campaign. Also, a folder of organizational material outlines the work of the Taxpayers Research Institute, the survey-and-analysis division of Taxpayers United.
  - Budgets and Financial Summaries (Box 1)
  - Campaign Circulars, Petitions, Worksheets (Box 1)
  - Election Returns November 1978 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes September 1978 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1976-1979, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Headlee, Richard H
    - Public Appearances for Taxpayers United (Box 1)
    - Speeches (Box 1)
  - Headquarters Manual and General Information (Box 1)
  - Legal Reviews of Tax Limitation Proposal (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1978 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles, Editorials 1978, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Press Information Kit 1977 (includes photos) (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Promotional Materials 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Radio, Television Reports and Editorials 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Shaker, William (founder) (Box 1)
  - Slideshow Materials
    - Audio Cassette Tape of Slide Script (Box 1)
    - Slide Script (Box 1)
  - Taxpayers Research Institute
    - Handbook of Organization (Box 1)
    - Survey Forms (Box 1)
    - Analyses of Surveys (Box 1)
- Taxpayers United Federation, Inc
  Three folders of material document the efforts of Taxpayers United Federation, Inc., the Lansing political interest group that lobbied in 1979 for full implementation of the "Headlee Amendment". The last series in this first accession - Topical Files - contains material of general reference to the 1978 tax amendment campaign. Of note is a comprehensive summary of the several tax amendments on the 1978 ballot. The summary was issued by the Michigan Senate Fiscal Agency.
  - General Correspondence 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Election Term Limitation Proposal (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  - Detroit Committee to Save Public Schools (Box 2)
  - Election Guide, League of Women Voters 1978 (Box 2)
  - Friedman, Milton (speeches, articles) (Box 2)
  - Governor's Commission on Ballot Proposal Implementation (Box 2)
  - Kelly, Frank J. (legal correspondence) (Box 2)
  - McMaster Associates (Public Relations Firm for Taxpayers United) (Box 2)
  - Murphy, Dan (speech) (Box 2)
  - "Tax Limitation" (periodical articles) (Box 2)
  - Tax Proposal Summaries, Senate Fiscal Agency 1978 (Box 2)
  - Tisch Tax Amendment Proposal 1978 (Box 2)
  - Vanek Tax Amendment Proposal 1978 (Box 2)
  - Welborn, Jack, Proposal to Implement "Headlee Amendment," May 1979 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1989-1991
  - 1989-1991 (Box 2)
- Headlee for Governor 1988, 1983-1988
  The Headlee for Governor series contains files related to Headlee's campaign for Governor in 1988 but unfortunately only contains copies of the documents pertaining to campaign income and expenses.
  - Annual Statements 1985-1987, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Campaign Statements 1983, 4 volumes (Box 2)
- Headlee Initiative
  The Headlee Initiative series contains files relating to the rejection of the initiative as a ballot proposal by the state board of canvassers and the resultant lawsuits and trials.
  - General 1990 (Box 2)
  - Board of Canvassers
    - General 1991, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Hearing 1991 (Box 2)
    - Court Appeals 1991-1992, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Contested Petitions, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - Legal Challenge
    - General 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Staff Briefing 1991 (Box 3)
  - Petitions
    - Blank 1990 (Box 3)
    - Challenged 1991 (Box 3)
    - Legal Information 1991 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Projected Effects 1991 (Box 3)
  - Sessa-Schmid Proposal 1989-1990 (Box 3)
- Taxpayers United for the Michigan Constitution
  - General 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Citizens for Newspaper Competition (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials consists of a folder of photographs of Headlee and other Michigan political figures taken in the early 1980s and four VHS videocassettes. Three of the cassettes are of appearances by Headlee on Detroit news programs; the fourth is of a 1991 speech at the Detroit Economic Club by Lt. Col. Oliver North, whom Headlee introduced. There is also an oversize colored drawing featuring caricatures of Headlee and other Michigan political figures.
  - Political Photographs, undated (Box 3)
  - Video Cassettes
    - Chamber of Commerce 05/09/1989 (Box 3)
    - "Mort Crim's Free 4 All," 09/30/1991 (Box 3)
    - "Legislative Salary Increases," 02/17/1993 (Box 3)
    - "Oliver North at Economic Club of Detroit," 11/06/1991 (Box 3)
- Clippings
  The largest series in the collection is Clippings. Dating from 1970 to 1990, this portion of the collection relates to the Alexander Hamilton Life Insurance Company, the Headlee Amendment and Headlee Initiative, Headlee himself and other miscellaneous topics. The majority of the series consists of photocopied articles from newspapers across Michigan covering the issue of tax reform, tax limitation, and the specifics of the Headlee Initiative.
  - Alexander Hamilton Life Insurance 01/01/1990-03/31/1990 (Box 4)
  - Headlee Amendment 02/15/1989-02/28/1990, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 3/90 (Box 4)
  - Proposals A and B 06/15/1989-11/15/1989, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1971-1981 (Box 4)
  - Richard H. Headlee 1981-1990 (Box 4)
  - Taxes 02/28/1990-12/31/1990 (Box 5)
  - Taxes 06/01/1991-03/31/1992, 21 folders (Box 5)
  - Taxes 04/01/1992-10/31/1992, 21 folders (Box 6)
  - Taxes 11/01/1992-09/30/1993, 17 folders (Box 7)